Now that we had look at references let's have a look at another awesome feature introduced by react 16.3,
Referanslara baktmzda, yeni balam API'sini serbest brakmak iin yeniden davranma 16 tarafndan sunulan bir
the new context API,
dizi harika zellie bir gz atalm.
a great tool for passing global state around in your app.
Avrupa'da kresel durumu ele geirmek iin harika bir ara.
Now what do I mean with that? Let's say in our cockpit here, in the cockpit.js file, we have a new button,
imdi bununla ne demek istediim kokpit bezemizin kokpitte dt yerde aaya dtmz dmenin altnda
below the button which we already have,
yeni bir dme var.
I'll add a second one and there I'll simply say login.
Ben ikinci bir tane ekleyeceim ve orada sonunda kilitlen.
Now this button once clicked should actually set some global login state to true and change something
imdi bu tua bir kez tklandnda, baz kresel oturum ama sahnelerini doru olarak ayarlamal ve
on different components.
farkl bileenlerde bir eyi deitirmelidir.
So i'll add a on click listener and let's say we got a prop here so I'll use props
Bu yzden bir tklatma dinleyicisi ekleyin ve diyelim ki burada bir destek aldk, bylece sahne kullanacam.
and then we got login.
Ve sonra giri yaptk.
So we need to pass down a login prop to that cockpit component which should hold a reference to a
Bu yzden, dmeye bastmzda altrlan bir ileve bir referans tutmas gereken lm kokpiti bileenine
function that is executed when we click the button.
ait bir kilidi aa doru geirmemiz gerekiyor.
So we go to the app.js file which is where we use the cockpit component here
Bu yzden, kokpit bileenini burada kullandmz asfalt yoluna gidiniz.
And I'll add my new login property here,
Ve yeni giriimi buraya ekleyeceim.
that's the one we passed down, we're extracting in the cockpit.
ldmz buydu, kokpitte kyoruz.
Now this should hold a reference to a method that gets executed
imdi bu idam edilen bir ynteme bir referans tutmaldr.
so let's add our login handler method here in our app.js file, and then here I want to change a state
Bu yzden log'umuzun ileyici yntemini Apogees dosyasmza ekleyelim ve burada bir state
that true toggles off the indication status,
det durumunu deitirmek istedim.
let's say. First of all let's assign the login handler as a function for the login prop and then
Her eyden nce, log ve Propp iin bir ilev olarak log in ileyicisini atayalm
I'll go up to my state of this app.js
ve sonra zapper durumuma gidelim.
file all the way up here and then simply add a new property to it authenticated which is false now
Evet, buraya kadar tm yol boyunca dn ve sonra, imdi yanl olan her ey iin yeni bir zellik ekleyin.
and it should be true once we click that button let's say. So down in the new login handler, I'll call
Ve bu dmeyi tkladktan sonra doru olmal ve sonra ileyiciye giri yapyorsunuz, hepsi
this.setState and I'll set authenticated to true,
bu set durumunu aryor ve ben true olarak ayarlanacam.
that's all I'm doing here.
Tm yaptm bu.
Now let's say I want to change something in my person component whenever
imdi diyelim ki her zaman kii bileenimdeki bir eyi deitirmek istiyorum.
this is set to true.
Bu doru olarak ayarlanm m.
Now what we can of course do is we can try to pass our states down to persons.
imdi elbette yapabileceimiz ey, devletlerimizi insanlara aktarmaya alabiliriz.
We can do this here, that on this persons array we're setting is authenticated prop and we set this equal
Bu yl, bu kiinin Irak'nda propp'u doruladmz ve bunu, bu kiinin
to this state authenticated. In the persons component
kendi bileenindeki sendikaya eit hale getirdiimizi syleyebiliriz.
we're getting this new prop and we can pass it down to the single person component,
Bu yeni pervaneyi alyoruz ve onu tek kiilik bileene aktarabiliriz.
we can pass down authenticated and this will refer to this props is authenticated so the prop we just
Kimlii dorulanm olabilir ve bu ilemin dorulanacan ve muhtemelen kurulumun yapldn ve de neden
set up in the app.js file
olacan ifade edeceiz.
and then the person component, we can then output some text if we are authenticated.
Ve sonra kii bileeni, eer krlrsak bir miktar metin karabiliriz.
So here let's use a ternary expression, we could say if this props authenticated, if this is true then
Yani burada, eer bu doruysa, o zaman dorulanmsa, bir paragrafta diyelim ki, bir paragraf
I want to output let's say a paragraph where I'll say I'm
tekrar syleyelim diyebiliriz, l bir ifade kullanalm.
authenticated
Hakl.
otherwise if this is not true, I want to output
Bu bir k iin doru deilse, Oberweis.
null.
imdi.
Now with that in place if we save that and we reload, if we click show persons, it works fine.
imdi, bunu kaydedersek ve biz tklamak iin yeniden yklyoruz.
and if I click this nice login button here, we see i'm authenticated and all the users.
Bir tklama gzel giri yaparsa, ancak burada gryorum ki, kimlii dorulanm ve tm kullanclar.
So this is working, we're passing data around.
Bu yzden bu veriyi aktaryoruz.
Now this is the default way of passing data around and it's the recommended way for most use cases
imdi bu, verileri iletmenin varsaylan yoludur ve ou kullanm durumu iin nerilen yoldur.
however you sometimes have some global state like the authentication status or for example regarding
Bununla birlikte, bazen kimlik dorulama durumu gibi bir global durumunuz veya rnein kullanc tarafndan oluturulan
a global theme color set up by the user,
genel bir tema rengine sahip olursunuz.
things like that.
Gibi eyler.
Now passing down the values is certainly an option but you can use the new context API to make this
imdi deerleri amak kesinlikle bir seenektir, ancak bunu daha kolay hale getirmek iin onu
a bit easier.
balam API'sinde kullanabilirsiniz.
It works like this,
Bu uygulamada byle alr.
in the app.js
Evet.
file, we first of all create context.
ncelikle ierik yaratn.
We do this out of the class, after the inputs and I'll store in a constant and I'll name it AuthContext,
Bunu snfn dna karp girdiler sunarak sabit olarak saklyoruz ve bunu balam
like this.
gibi adlandryorum.
We do that with react create context so a new method introduced by react 16.3
Bunu yeniden harekete geirerek balam yaratrz, bu yzden yeniden serbeste 16 tarafndan sunulan yeni bir yntem.
and there I can set up a default value like false for authentication, false,
Ve orada kimlik dorulama yanl iin yanl gibi bir varsaylan deer ayarlayabilirsiniz.
this is optional though,
Bu istee bal olsa da.
the more important part is how we used the AuthContext.
Daha nemli olan, kapal balam nasl kullandmzdr.
We do that in our jsx code and AuthContext or context in general works with providers and consumers.
Bunu GSX kodumuzda ve genel olarak ierik salayclar ve tketicilerle birlikte ierik veya balamda yapyoruz.
We got paths in our app where we provide the context and others where we consume it. Now in the app.js file,
Laboratuvarmzda, ierii saladmz ve bilinen asfalt nerede kullandmzn bir paras var.
this is where we provide it because here we managed the authentication status.
Burada saladmz yer buras, burada sizin hakllnz ynetiyoruz.
So now we're wrapping all components where we plan on extracting that value from the context with a
imdi, bu bileeni balamdan kardnz zel bir bileenle balamdan bu deeri
special component, the AuthContext component.
karmay planladmz tm bileenleri saryoruz.
Now the name of the component simply is the name of this constant here,
imdi, bileen ismi sadece bu sabitin addr.
So create context creates a component you can use in jsx.
Bu yzden balam yaratmak, GSX'i kullanabileceiniz bir bileen oluturur.
So now we got the AuthContext component,
imdi kapal balam bileenini aldk.
however we don't use AuthContext like this
Ancak balam byle kullanmyoruz.
instead we access .provider, a subcomponent created by react so to say, and this is also what we close
Bunun yerine, nokta salaycsna tepkinin yaratt bir alt bileene eriiyoruz ve bu da burada daha
here with the closing tag. Now persons is wrapped with AuthContext provider, another important building block
da geni ve nemli bir yap ta iin kapal balamla kapatlm olan kapan etiketiyle kapandmz ey.
now is the value.
imdi deer vermektir.
Now we get that initial value of false because we initialized create context with false
imdi bu ilk deeri veya yanl aldk nk balam sahte ile oluturmaya baladk.
but if you want to have a dynamic value which can change, we add the value prop and note this has to be
Ancak, deiebilen dinamik bir deere sahip olmak istiyorsanz, vekaletname ve ihbar, borlu
named value to that AuthContext provider component and we set it equal to the value we want to use
kontekst bileenine bor vermemiz gerekir ve biz onu kullanmak istediimiz deere eit tutarz.
and this value can of course change.
Ve devalasyon elbette deiebilir.
So here I'll set it to this state authenticated and it will change whenever the state changes.
Bu yzden onu kimliklendirilen bu duruma ayarlyorum ve devlet her deitiinde deiecek.
So now we're providing this context to all child components in there, no matter on which level they are
imdi bu balam, hangi seviyede olursa olsun, tm alt bileenlere sunuyoruz.
so to say and this of course is only one here but this could be more,
Demek ki, bu elbette sadece bir yldr ama bu daha fazla olabilir.
and this one component actually holds more than one component.
Ve bu bir bileen aslnda birden fazla bileen ierir.
So in the persons component, we can now get rid of that authenticated prop we're passing down to the single
Bylece kii bileeninde u anda kimlii dorulanm Propp'ten kurtulabiliyoruz
person and on the app.js, we can also get rid of the this.authenticated.prop we're passing down to
ki tek bir kiiye ve yakalamaya geiyoruz. Evet, ayn zamanda bizden de kurtulabiliyoruz.
persons and with that removed, we can go down to a single person component and this is where we want
kaldrlan tek bir kii bileenine gidebiliriz ve bu bizim balam hakkmz
to use our context right.
kullanmak istediimiz yerdir.
So first of all we need to be able to import it
ncelikle onu ithal edebilmemiz gerekiyor.
so we go back to the app.js file and we simply export our AuthContext here,
Bu yzden, mthi bir de geri dnyoruz ve sadece kapal balammz buraya ihra ediyoruz.
this makes it available outside of this file too. We can now go to our single person files not to persons,
Bu, bu Faltu'nun dnda bir balina gezintisi yapar, imdi tek insanmza gidebiliriz, iki kii dmez.
this is now what we need to work on,on person and in here, in our person component, we now simply import
Bu kii zerinde almak iin garip olan bir eydir ve buradaki kii bileenimizde bu ierii basite
this context.
ie aktaryoruz.
So we import AuthContext from
Bylece tm ierii ie aktaryoruz.
and now we need to go up all the way to our app.js
Ve imdi uyguladmz yere kadar gitmeliyiz.
file. We import AuthContext and now we need to wrap the element where we want to use that context
JS dosyas balam ie aktaryoruz ve imdi bu balam deerini kullanmak istediimiz eyi
value.
sarmalamamz gerekiyor.
In our case it's this first line here, there I now create a new component AuthContext, but now not provider
Bizim durumumuzda buradaki ilk satr, imdi balamn yeni bir bileenini yaratyorum ama imdi
but consumer because now we'll consume that value stored in the context and I'll simply wrap this entire
salayc deil, tketici. nk imdi bu balamda saklanan deeri tketecek
expression here with our AuthContext consumer component.
ve bu ifadenin tamamn, balam d tketici bileenimizle kaplayacam.
Now in here, in this consumer component, we still use single curly braces but there we need to execute
imdi burada bu tketici bileeninde hala tek kal ayralar kullanyoruz ama orada
a method which react will execute for us.
yeniden harekete geecek bir yntem yrtmemiz gerekiyor.
This method receives one argument and this is the data we're passing down with the context,
Bu yntem tek bir argman alr ve bunu balam ile aktardmz verileri yapar.
this could of course be an object, in our case it's a boolean.
Bu, elbette bizim olgumuzda bir nesne olabilir, bir boole.
So here it's our auth state and we return the jsx we want to render.
Yani burada bizim kapal durumumuz ve render etmek istediimiz GSX'e dnyoruz.
Now in our case we no longer need to check props authenticated,
imdi bizim durumumuzda, pervanenin kimliini dorulamamza gerek yok.
we just check if auth, which remember is a boolean for us is true in which case we're rendering this,
Sadece hangi bir hatrlamann bizim iin bir Milyar olduunu doru olup olmadn kontrol ediyoruz, bu durumda buna giriyoruz.
otherwise, we render nothing.
Aksi halde hibir ey yapmayz.
And now, we're taking advantage of the context API react 16.3 introduced
Ve imdi, balam API'sini kullanan 600 cretsiz Intrade'in yeniden kullanlmasndan yararlanyoruz.
and we can pass data around without having to set up this chain of props.
Ve bu sahne zincirini kurmak zorunda kalmadan veriyi iletebiliriz.
If now reload this component, we click show persons and we click login,
imdi bu kiileri tkladmz tklayn.
we still see I'm authenticated
Hala grmezden geldiimizi gryoruz.
but now without passing around props. Still the props approach is recommended for most cases,
Ama imdi sahne evresinde gemeden hala birok durumda sahne yaklam tavsiye edilir.
it makes your components more reusable and doesn't tie them together that much.
Bileenlerinizi tekrar kullanlabilir hale getirir ve bu kadar birletirmez.
However the context API is really great for global settings like this one.
Ancak, ierik API'si, bunun gibi genel ayarlar iin gerekten harika.